A Guide to the Abraham Pais papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA014
Rockefeller Archive Center
Abraham Pais papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1875-2000
bulk 1936-1998
Rockefeller Archive Center
Pais, Abraham
Rockefeller University
FA014
35.3 Cubic Feet 96 document cases
Arrangement note
The Abraham Pais Papers are arranged in 8 series:
Series 1 - Biographical
Series 2 - Manuscripts
Subseries 1 - Niels Bohr
Subseries 2 - Paul Dirac
Subseries 3 - Albert Einstein
Subseries 4 - Inward Bound
Subseries 5 - A Tale of Two Continents
Subseries 6 - Essays, Articles and Unpublished Manuscripts
Series 3 - Subject Files
Series 4 - Lectures
Series 5 - Correspondence
Series 6 - Notes and Notebooks
Series 7 - Photos
Series 8 - Reprints
Biographical/Historical note
Abraham Pais (1918-2000), a theoretical physicist, was one of the first founders of particle physics. He was Detlev W. Bronk Professor Emeritus at the Rockefeller University. Known for his work with the forces that control particle interaction, including the development of the principle of associated production, Pais was also a noted historian of science. In the latter part of his career Pais became known for his histories of physics, most notably "Inward Bound: Of Matter and Forces in the Physical World," and his biographies of Albert Einstein, "Subtle is the Lord," and Niels Bohr, "Niels Bohr's Times." Professor Pais died on July 28, 2000.
Chronology
May 19, 1918 Born in Amsterdam, The Netherlands to Jesaja and Kaatje Pais.
November 1, 1920 Sister Annie born.
1935 Obtained high school diploma from HBS (Higher Burgher School) in Amsterdam. Began studies at the University of Amsterdam.
1936 Joined the NZSO (Zionist student organization).
Spring 1938 Graduated with two bachelor's degrees in physics and mathematics from the University of Amsterdam. Pais also minored in chemistry and astronomy.
Fall 1938 Enrolled in the University of Utrecht to continue graduate studies under George E. Uhlenbeck and Hendrik Casimir.
July 9, 1941 Awarded PhD. from University of Utrecht.
March 1943 Went into hiding from the Gestapo to avoid deportation.
1945 First publications, in the "Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical Society," "Transactions of the Dutch Academy of Sciences," "Physical Review," "Nature" and "Physica."
January 1946 Research fellow to Niels Bohr at the Institute of Theoretical Physics in Copenhagen, Denmark.
September 1946 Came to the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, New Jersey. Temporary Member.
1949 Full-time member of the Institute for Advanced Study.
1950 Professor at the Institute for Advanced Study.
1951 Began development of the "principle of associated production."
1955 Visiting professor at Columbia University.
May 1956 Attended the First All-Union Conference on the Physics of Particles at High Energies in Moscow [the first post-war conferenence with American participation].
December 15, 1956 Married first wife, Lila Atwill. Had one son, Joshua in 1958. Divorced in 1961.
October 1961 Attended the Twelfth Solvay Conference.
1962 Elected a member of the National Academy of Sciences.
1963 Became a professor of physics at the Rockefeller University.
1965 Co-discovered the theory of "particle-mixing" and work with the SU(6) theory.
1976 Married second wife, Sara. Divorced in 1985.
1977 Visiting Professor at the Weizmann Institute in Israel. Named the James Arthur Balfour Professor at the Institute.
1979 Awarded the 11th Annual J. Robert Oppenheimer Memorial Prize.
1981 Named Detlev W. Bronk Professor at the Rockefeller University.
1982 Published "Subtle is the Lord: The Science and the Life of Albert Einstein."
1986 Published "Inward Bound: Of Matter and Forces in the Physical World."
1988 Professor Emeritus at the Rockefeller University.
March 15, 1990 Married Ida Nicolaisen.
1991 Published "Niels Bohr's Times: In Physics, Philosophy, and Polity."
1992 Received the Physics Prize from the Netherlands Physical Society.
1993 Awarded the Medal of Science from the Royal Dutch Academy of Sciences. Received the Germant Award of the American Institute of Physics.
1994 Published "Einstein Lived Here: Essays for the Layman."
1995 Awarded the Lewis Thomas Prize.
1997 Published "A Tale of Two Continents: A Physicists Life in a Turbulent World," his autobiography.
2000 Published "The Genius of Science: A Portrait Gallery of Twentieth Century Physicists."
July 28, 2000 Died from heart failure in Copenhagen, Denmark.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, subject files, photographs, manuscripts, lectures, and biographical material documenting the work of Abraham Pais.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 450 P166
Nuclear physics; Physics; Quantum theory; Statistical physics; Unified field theories; Field theory (Physics); Strong interactions (Nuclear physics)
- Biographical, 1934-2000; 1; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes a bibliography of Abraham Pais and assorted biographical sources. It also includes printed biographical material on his widow, a wedding guest book, and assorted personal papers including passports and World War II identification papers.
  - Biographies and Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Celebration of the Life of Abraham Pais, [September 13, 2000] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Driving Permits and Related Documents, [1956-1957] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ida Nicolaisen, 1989-1999; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ida Nicolaisen, 1991-1997; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Old Passports, 1947-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pais, A. - Personal, 1942-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pais, A. - Personal, December 1949-March 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal Varia, 1954-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from scholarly access.
  - Rockefeller University - "News & Notes", [2000] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Varia, 1955-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - War - Personal Documents, 1934-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Wedding Guest Book, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Manuscripts, 1875-2000; 2; 8.5 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into 6 subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Niels Bohr
  Subseries 2 - Paul Dirac
  Subseries 3 - Albert Einstein
  Subseries 4 - "Inward Bound"
  Subseries 5 - "A Tale of Two Continents"
  Subseries 6 - Essays, Articles and Unpublished Manuscripts
  The material in each subseries is arranged by format and alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of reference notes, manuscripts, and publication materials related to the 5 books published by Abraham Pais: biographies of Niels Bohr, Paul Dirac, and Albert Einstein; "Inward Bound;" and "A Tale of Two Continents." There are also essays, articles and unpublished manuscripts, found in Subseries 6.
  - Niels Bohr, 1912-2000; 1
    The material in this subseries is arranged by format and alphabetically.
    The materials for this book are broken down in order of the publication process, beginning with Reference notes that include material collected on the subject matter such as handwritten notes, newspaper and journal articles, as well as copies of book chapters and other related archival material depending on the subject. This is followed by the Manuscripts which include both handwritten and typed drafts of chapters of the different books. The last section is Publication and this includes primarily correspondence with the publishers, edits to the books, copies of the book covers and reviews of the books.
    - NB Biographical, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - NB Biographical, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - NB Bibliography, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Interviews with NB, 1959-1962; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - NB Interviews, 1962-1964; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - [Niels Bohr Reminiscences], [1961-1963, 1983]; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - [Reminiscences about] Niels Bohr, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - [Bohr Correspondence with E. Rutherford], 1912-1934, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Niels Bohr - [Unpublished Manuscript] "beta-Ray Spectra and Energy Conservation", 1929 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Harold Höffding, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Niels Bohr Unpublished Manuscripts, 1932-1937, 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Reference Notes - Festskrift til Professor Niels Bohr, October 7, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Reference Notes - Bohr Stuff, 1937, 1957, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Reference Notes - Bohr Stuff, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Reference Notes - [Correspondence with Hendrik Kramers], [1942] (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Aage's Memorandum - Washington, D.C., July 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - [Pais Correspondence with Aage Bohr], [1946] (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Bohr Correspondence, 1946, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Politics, Postwar and Open Letter, 1948-1966, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - [Bohr Correspondence with W. Pauli], [1950, 1955] (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - [Miscellaneous Loose Manuscripts about Niels Bohr], [1954-1963, 1983] (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Reference Notes - Niels' Saga, October 1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Reference Notes - [Copy of Letter from Niels Bohr to United Nations], [1956] (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Reference Notes - [Excerpts from Books on Felix Frankfurter], [1965-1974] (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Reference Notes - War, Postdocs, 1968-1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Opening Pages, Table of Contents, To the Reader], undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 1: Themes], undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 2: In Denmark I was born....], undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 3: Boyhood], undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 4: Toward the Twentieth Century....], undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 5: Natura facit saltum], undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 6: Student Days], undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 7: In which Bohr goes to England....], undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 8: Bohr, father of the atom], undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 9: How Bohr secured his permanent base of operations], undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 10: Mathematics in physics], undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 11: Bohr and Einstein], undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 12: A modern Viking who comes on a great errand], undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 13: Then the whole picture changes completely....], undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 14: The Spirit of Copenhagen], undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 15: Looking into the atomic nucleus], undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 16: Toward the edge of physics in the Bohr style, and a bit beyond], undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 17: How Bohr orchestrated experimental progress in the thirties, in physics and biology], undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 18: Of sad events and of major journeys], undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 19: We are suspended in language], undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 20: Fission], undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 21: Bohr, pioneer of "glasnost"], undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 22: In which Bohr moves full steam ahead into his later years], undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [Chapter 23: Epilog], undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript Drafts - [A chronology], undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Publication - Illustrations, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Publication - A. P. Sloan (N.B.), 1987-2000 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Publication - Random House, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Publication - Niels Bohr - OUP [Oxford University Press] Contract and Subsequent Correspondence, 1990-1995 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Publication - NB's Times, 1991-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Paul Dirac, 1935-1996; 2
    - Reference Notes, 1978-1996 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Dirac Reprints, 1935-1952 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Dirac Reprints, 1953-1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Dirac Reprints, 1964-1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Changes for Manuscript, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Photographs and Slides, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Albert Einstein, 1875-1999; 3
    Manuscript material for Chapters 26-28 was not in the collection.
    - Albert Einstein Biographical, 1875-1948 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Albert Einstein Biographical, 1950-1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Albert Einstein Biographical, 1980-1982, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Post Scripta, 1879-1981; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Post Scripta, 1982-1985, n.d.; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - [Xerox of Einstein Certificate], [1902] (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes, 1904, 1927, 1972, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Reference Notes - AE Papers, 1905-1906, 1921-1950, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Reference Notes - AE Letters, 1905-1955, 1972-1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Bose-Einstein Stat, 1924-1938, 1953-1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - Einstein IAS [Institute for Advanced Study] Files, 1932-1954 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Dukas/Nathan, 1955, 1977-1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - De Broglie, Einstein and the Birth of the Matter Wave Concept, 1978, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - F.B.I. Einstein File, 1981, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Dukas Testament, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript - First Thoughts, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript - Title Page and Preface, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript - To the Reader, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 1 - Purpose and Plan, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 1 - Purpose and Plan, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 2 - New Kinds of Rays, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 3 - Portrait of a Physicist as a Young Man, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 4 - Of Molecules and Entropy and Many Other Things, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 5 - The Reality of Molecules, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 6 - "Subtle is the Lord....", undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 7 - The New Kinematics, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 8 - The Edge of History, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 9 - Relativity, the General Theory, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 10 - Herr Professor Einstein, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 11 - The Prague Papers, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 12 - The Einstein-Grossman Collaboration, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 13 - Field Theories of Gravitation: the First Fifty Years, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 14 - The Field Equations of Gravitation, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 15 - The New Dynamics, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 16 - The Suddenly Famous Doctor Einstein, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 17 - Unified Field Theory, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 18 - Preliminaries, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 19 - The Light Quantum, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 20 - Einstein and Specific Heats, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 21 - The Photon, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 22 - Interlude: The BKS Proposal, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 23 - A Loss of Identity: the Birth of Quantum Statistics, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 24 - Einstein as a Transitional Figure: The Birth of Wave Mechanics, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 25 - Einstein's Response to the New Dynamics, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 29 - Of Tensors and a Hearing Aid and Many Other Things: Einstein's Collaborators, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Manuscript - Chapter 30 - How Einstein Got the Nobel Prize, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Manuscript - "Einstein Lived Here" - Chapters 9 & 10, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Manuscript - "Einstein Lived Here" - Chapter 11: Einstein and the Jews, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript - Albert Einstein Centennial, 1977-1979; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript - Albert Einstein Centennial, 1977-1979; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript - Albert Einstein Centennial, 1977-1979; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript - "Physics Today", August 1994 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Publication - Einstein RMP, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Publication - Permissions, 1979-1982 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Publication - OUP [Oxford University Press] - Dr. Pais, 1980-1982 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Publication - OUP [Oxford University Press], 1980-1985 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Publication - "S. is the L." Letters, 1980-1985 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      "Subtle is the Lord"
    - Publication - "Subtle is the Lord", 1982-1984 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Publication - "Subtle is the Lord" Reviews, 1982-1985 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Publication - AE Corrections, 1982-1986 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Publication - Russian Translation, 1984-1990 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Publication - German Translation, 1985-1988 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Publication - Italian and Brazilian Translation, 1985-1990, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Publication - French Translation, 1985-1999 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Publication - Japanese Translation, 1986-1987, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Publication - Chinese Translation, 1986-1990, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Publication - French Translation, 1988, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Publication - Serbo-Croatian Translation, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Publication - Einstein Lived Here - Translations, 1994-1996 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Publication - Einstein Lived Here, 1994-1997 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "Inward Bound", 1897-1988; 4
    Manuscript material for Chapters 5, 7, 13, and 17 was not in the collection.
    - Reference Notes - Research Correspondence [Publication Dates: 1905-1984], 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 1 - Purpose and Plan, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 2 - New Kinds of Rays: Part (a) Roentgen, undated (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 2 - New Kinds of Rays: Part (b) Becquerel, undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 3 - From Uranic Rays to Radioactivity; Part (a) The Curies, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 3 - From Uranic Rays to Radioactivity; Part (b) Rutherford, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 4 - The First Particle, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 4 - The First Particle, undated; Chapter 5 is not in the collection; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 6 - Radioactivity's Three Early Puzzles, undated; Chapter 7 is not in the collection. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 8 - beta-Spectra, 1907-1914, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 9 - Atomic Structure and Spectral Lines, undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 9 - Atomic Structure and Spectral Lines, undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 9 - Atomic Structure and Spectral Lines, undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 10 - 'It was the epoch of belief, it was the epoch of incredulity', undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 11 - Nuclear Physics' Tender Age, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 12 - Quantum Mechanics, An Essay, undated; Chapter 13 is not in the collection (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 14 - Nuclear Physics, the Age of Paradox, undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 14 - Nuclear Physics, the Age of Paradox, undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 14 - Nuclear Physics, the Age of Paradox, undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 15 - Quantum Fields, or How Particles Are Made and How They Disappear, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 16 - Battling the Infinite, undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 16 - Battling the Infinite, undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 16 - Battling the Infinite, undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 16 - Battling the Infinite; Part (d) Quantum Electrodynamics in the Thirties, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 16 - Battling the Infinite; Part (d) Quantum Electrodynamics in the Thirties, undated; Chapter 17 is not in the collection; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 18 - Of Quantum Electrodynamics' Triumphs and Limitations and of a New Particle's Sobering Impact; Part (a) Shelter Island, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 18 - Of Quantum Electrodynamics' Triumphs and Limitations and of a New Particle's Sobering Impact; Part (b) Muons, undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 18 - Of Quantum Electrodynamics' Triumphs and Limitations and of a New Particle's Sobering Impact; Part (b) Muons, undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 18 - Of Quantum Electrodynamics' Triumphs and Limitations and of a New Particle's Sobering Impact; Part (b) Muons, undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 19 - In Which Particle Physics Enters the Era of Big Machines and Big Detectors and Pion Physics Goes Through Ups and Downs, undated; Folder 1 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 19 - In Which Particle Physics Enters the Era of Big Machines and Big Detectors and Pion Physics Goes Through Ups and Downs, undated; Folder 2 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 20 - Onset of an Era: New Forms of Matter Appear, Old Symmetries Crumble, undated; Folder 1 of 3 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 20 - Onset of an Era: New Forms of Matter Appear, Old Symmetries Crumble, undated; Folder 2 of 3 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 20 - Onset of an Era: New Forms of Matter Appear, Old Symmetries Crumble, undated; Folder 3 of 3 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 21 - Essay on Modern Times: 1960-1983, undated; Folder 1 of 4 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 21 - Essay on Modern Times: 1960-1983, undated; Folder 2 of 4 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 21 - Essay on Modern Times: 1960-1983, undated; Folder 3 of 4 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Reference Notes - Chapter 21 - Essay on Modern Times: 1960-1983, undated; Folder 4 of 4 (Box 18, Folder 6)